<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Cranmerian liturgy, or, The subtilty of the serpent in corrupting the true English liturgy, by Cranmer and a faction of Calvinists.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61427</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5425A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R222003</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833242</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833242</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37717</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61427)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37717)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2063:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Cranmerian liturgy, or, The subtilty of the serpent in corrupting the true English liturgy, by Cranmer and a faction of Calvinists.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37717:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The CRANMERIAN LITURGY, <hi>Or, The Subtilty of the Serpent, In corrupting the</hi> True Engliſh Liturgy, <hi>by</hi> Cranmer <hi>and a Faction of</hi> Calviniſts.</head>
            <p>THat there is in the moſt Solemn, Proper and Peculiar part of the Chriſtian Worſhip, anciently in all the Weſtern Churches intitled <hi>the Maſs,</hi> now in Engliſh <hi>the H. Communion,</hi> as it hath always been celebrated throughout the whole Catholic Church, not a Sacrament only, but both a Sacrifice and a Sacrament, hath been the Doctrin not only of the Catholic Church in all Ages received from the Apoſtles, and accordingly it was called <hi>Sacrificium Quotidianum,</hi> but alſo of moſt of thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who Compoſed the Firſt Book of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. and upon good Deliberation and ſpecial Conſideration of the Queſtion fitted it for that purpoſe; &amp; moreover of divers of the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for Learning in <hi>England</hi> ever ſince; as <hi>Andrews, Feild, Montague, Couſens, Laud, Mede, Heylyn, Thorndike, Taylor, Sherlock, Hooper</hi> &amp;c. As may be ſeen or perceived in their Writings; beſides others, who are known to have been of the ſame Judgment, though they have left nothing in writing concerning it; and others, who out of Fondneſs for the Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they were Members, affecting a kind of Infallibility, and preferring the Honour of it, before the Honour and Unity of the Catholic Church, and Peace of the World, have rather cavilled at it, then could in their Conſcience plainly and poſitively deny it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Cranmer</hi> with his Calviniſts, who were amongſt them, who compoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Book, being unable to carry all in that work according to his own mind, in an Honeſt, Plain, Orderly way, preſently applied himſelf to do it by Craft and the Secular Power, though in a Factious and Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical manner: And <hi>a Review</hi> of that Book, though but juſt before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by Act of Parliament to have been <hi>compoſed by the Aid of the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi> was ſoon preſumptuouſly, if not impiouſly, reſolved upon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any worthy cauſe, as the next Act ſaith expreſly: And inſtead of an Engliſh Synod or Convocation of the Engliſh Clergy, (not one of them it ſeems, but had either ſo much Conſcience or ſo much Caution, as not to appear in it,) <hi>Martin Bucer</hi> was ſent for from beyond Sea, and the Book was tranſlated into Latin for him to conſider and model according to his own and Maſter <hi>Calvin's</hi> humour, <hi>ad Petitionem Archiepiſcopi,</hi> as far as was thought fit, and like to paſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucer</hi> did what was deſired, and preſuming too much upon his own Judgment, and perhaps the more thro' the over valuation of it by <hi>Cranmer</hi> and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:37717:2"/>his Faction, tho' he might mean well, diſmembred, diſordered and deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it in the principal part, as may be ſeen in his <hi>Scripta Anglicana;</hi> but was ſoon after call'd to account for what he had done, in another World. tho' I do not find that all the Corruptions and Abuſes in it are chargeable upon him, and particularly that, which was none of the leaſt, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing and Miſplacing the Prayer of Oblation, of which more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. But he was farther imploy'd to promote the Work by writing to Mr <hi>Calvin,</hi> that by his Perſwaſions and Authority, the Protector, and the King himſelf, and other great men might be diſpoſed for the paſſing it in Parliament, whether the Clergy would or not.</p>
            <p>And ſo the <hi>New Book</hi> was approved by the King, the <hi>Young Head</hi> of the <hi>New Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and by him now grown up to fifteen, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inſtructed in the <hi>New Doctrin,</hi> recommended to <hi>the Parliament,</hi> ſo taken up with the Spoils of the Monaſteries, as left little leaſure to think of <hi>Liturgies;</hi> and by them impoſed upon the Church and Nation, without any Synod or Convocation, or declared Conſent or Privity of any one of the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who is known to have had any hand in the Alterations, beſides <hi>Cranmer;</hi> and upon mere Politick Conſiderations, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other juſt Cauſe, as is declared by the Act it ſelf, by which it was eſtabliſhed</p>
            <p>And this is <hi>the true Generation of this</hi> ſpurious, ſuppoſititious, deformed <hi>Cranmerian Changling;</hi> which hath been hug'd by a company of ignorant, inconſiderate abuſed People, like a Baſtard child by a ſilly abuſed Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, made a Bone of Diſſention, and ridiculouſly contended for in ſeveral ſmall matters, by ſuch as were ſhamefully impoſed upon in the greateſt of all, and therein very tamely and weakly complyed with ſuch as had put the Abuſe upon them; an Abuſe not eaſy to be digeſted, or thought on without ſome Motion of Indignation by any intelligent perſon, who hath any Senſe of, and Concern for the Honour of God, of our Saviour, or of his Church, the true Catholic Church, or any remainder of it in this Nation. But in ſhort, this is matter of Fact, not to be denyed; and upon this matter of Fact two things are to be inquired:</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>what Spirit this might be done? Whether by the Spirit of Chriſt, or the Spirit of Antichriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>How far, or Whether at all, one having Knowledge, or Notice of this Abuſe ought or may uſe this imperfect and diſordered Form, or comply with it, by reaſon of any Humane Law, or of his own Subſcription before Notice or any Knowledge of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which may be added a third and fourth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Whether the People may communicate in the uſe of it, and not be Partakers in the Guilt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Whether the Clergy in general, and every particular perſon of them ought not to uſe in the Celebration of theſe Holy Miſteries a more Compleat and Perfect Form, notwithſtanding any temporal Laws to the contrary, as they will anſwer it to God upon the Salvation of their Souls at the laſt day?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37717:2"/>
            <p> The Firſt of theſe Queſtions may eaſily be reſolved upon a due Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Alterations,</hi> which were made; of which there are 4 or 5 Very Conſiderable, and notoriouſly <hi>Contrary to the Practice of the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic</hi> Church in the three Principal parts of that Office: In the Prayer for the Catholic Church, the <hi>Commemoration of the Saints,</hi> and <hi>Prayers for the Dead:</hi> In the Prayer of Conſecration that part, wherein the Greek Churches and all Antiquity place the very <hi>Form of Conſecration:</hi> And the whole Prayer <hi>of Oblation:</hi> the three former expunged and the laſt not only maimed of a principal part, but the remainder removed from its proper place, and moſt perverſly plac'd after the Communion.</p>
            <p>In all theſe Alterations ſo <hi>Conſiderable</hi> in themſelves, and moreover in reſpect to the Reverence which ought to be uſed toward the Holy-Spirit of God, and the regard to be had to the Honour of the State, if there appear no Conſiderable Advantage to the State to excuſe them, nor any thing really for the Honour or Service of God, which required them, but much to the contrary, with great and manifeſt Gratifications of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Powers, the Devil and his Angels, it will not be unreaſonable to believe that they were made by the Importunity of <hi>Cranmer,</hi> Arch-Biſhop and God-father to the King, and thro' the Inſtigation and Energy of thoſe Powers, by whom he was deluded.</p>
            <p>That there was no ſuch Advantage to the State appears by the very Act it ſelf: Nor have I ever yet known any thing alleadged or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in them for the Honour or Service of God, that had ſo much weight as deſerved to be taken notice of: But on the contrary in them all there is one <hi>Common Gratification</hi> of the Spight and Malice of the Spirit of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> againſt both the <hi>Catholic-Church,</hi> by contempt of the Authority of it, and ſuch a Breach and Diviſion in it; and againſt the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in particular, by making it Guilty of ſo execrable <hi>Schiſm</hi> and Sepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the whole Catholic-Church of all Ages, with great Preſumption and Indignity to it, by ſo inſolently rejecting, and by conſequence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning, ſo many ſuch Solemn Acts of her Worſhip: and this not mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the Church Militant, but extending even to the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, and Communion of Saints.</p>
            <p>For beſides all this, in the Expunging of <hi>the Commemoration of the Saints,</hi> there was a <hi>Special Gratification</hi> of their Spite and Malice againſt Them, by whom, and in whom, by Chriſt reſiding in them, they had been ſo often o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome; and even againſt Chriſt their Head, and God, the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: For the Thankſgiving to God for the Grace communicated to them, which was a Principal Fruit of Chriſt's Paſſion, being a Duty to God, and an Honour to Chriſt, in the Honour done to them, and a moſt Solemn Act of Communion of Saints, anſwered by them in their Prayers for the Church upon Earth; To have all this aboliſhed was undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly matter of much Joy and Tryumph in the whole Kingdom of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37717:3"/>
            <p> And ſuch another Special Gratification of their Spight and Malice was the Expunging of the Common <hi>Prayers</hi> of this Office <hi>for the Souls of the reſt departed</hi> in the Faith of Chriſt and Communion of the Catholic Church, by the Interruption of ſo Solemn an Act of the Church, of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to them and Communion with them.</p>
            <p>In the due <hi>Conſecration of the Euchariſt</hi> it hath always been believed in the Catholic Church that there is a Special <hi>Sanctification of the Elements</hi> of Bread and Wine by the Deſcent of the Holy Spirit at the Prayers of the Church: In the putting out therefore of that Prayer there is <hi>a double Gratification</hi> of that Malicious Spirit, 1. By the Injury or Diſreſpect thereby done to the Holy Spirit, by whom the Oblation ſhould be Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by whoſe Aid the former book was declared to have been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. (a ſpecial Inſtance of the Madneſs and Inconſiderateneſs of Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.) and 2. by depriving the Church of the Benefit of that Prayer, and making the Conſecration at leaſt doubtfull, but none at all according to the Sentiments of the greateſt part of Chriſtians at this day, and generally of all anciently as may be beleived upon the Agreement of all Ancient Liturgies in what is here put out; and that by Tradition from the Apoſtles, as is affirmed by S. <hi>Baſil.</hi> Nor is it much to be wondered to ſee ſuch Decay of Primitive Fervor and Vigor, when we ſee ſuch Departure from Primitive Inſtitutions, and Orders, and ſuch Neglect and Contempt of ſo Divine Means of Spiritual Supplies.</p>
            <p>Nor was it without ſome particular Gratification of the ſame wicked Spirit that the uſe of the <hi>Sign of the Croſs</hi> was alſo left off at the Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, contrary to the Practice of the whole Catholic Church derived from the Primitive times. The Victories obtained by Holy Chriſtians over the Powers of Darkneſs by the Uſe of that Sign (for which the Engliſh Reader may have recourſe to Dr. <hi>Caves</hi> Lives of the Fathers, and others) are an Evidence of their Abhorance of it; and that of the true Original of the like Abhorance in the minds of ſome men, from what Spirit it proceeds.</p>
            <p>But <hi>the Subtilty of</hi> the Serpent, as well as his Malice is in none of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations more remarkable, then in thoſe of <hi>the Prayer of Oblation,</hi> which <hi>Bucer</hi> did not think fit to alter, yet were made and deſigned purpoſely to aboliſh all that might import <hi>the Oblation of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbloody Sacrifice.</hi> And that was done as affectually as could be, in this manner: 1. It muſt not be quite taken away, leſt that ſhould give occaſion for ſome conteſt about it. but 2. It muſt be exenterated and the Heart taken out; and then 3. be placed after the Communion, ſo that then the Memorials could not be offered or preſented to God, which were eaten and drunk by the people; whereby the buſineſs was efectually done. And yet this was not enough, but 4. <hi>Another Prayer</hi> muſt be added to be uſed, the one or the other, at diſcretion, that ſo none might be obliged to the uſe of ſo much as that; and they who underſtood the Myſtery of it, needed not to be troubled with any relick of it, or the Spirit, which inſpired them, with the Memory
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:37717:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>of a thing ſo offenſive to him. And yet was not all this enough, but after all even the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> it ſelf muſt alſo be diſplaced, contrary to the uſe of the Catholic Church in all Ages, that ſo all the Prayers of this Church might be Schiſmatically ſeparated, and ſet at a Diſtance from the Memorials of our Saviours Sacrifice upon the Croſs, through which alone they have Acceptance. And if from the beginning of this Service we do but take notice how the <hi>Special Confeſſions</hi> in uſe in the Greek as well as Latine Churches are by a very formal <hi>General Confeſſion and Abſolution</hi> ſuperſeded and brought into diſuſe, we may obſerve the ſame Subtilty from end to end throughout. Such is the <hi>Subtilty of Schiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Superſtition inſpired by a Spirit of Deluſion,</hi> and impoſed upon inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate People, under a falſe Cover of Zeal for God againſt Superſtition.</p>
            <p>Nor are <hi>the Gratifications</hi> leſs remarkable than the Subtilty. The <hi>Matter of Fact</hi> is plain in the Books; and <hi>the Deſign</hi> not only eaſily perceivable in the Alterations, but moreover owned and expreſly affirm'd in the Charge and Allegations of the Scotiſh and Engliſh <hi>Calviniſts</hi> (who better underſtood the Myſtery of all, than the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> did, or were willing for ſhame to acknowledge) againſt <hi>Archbiſhop Laud</hi> for reſtoring it. And had it been a Fault, he had been really guilty of it; but was really guilty of Preferring the Honour of his particular Church before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Lord and his Catholic Church; and not faithfully and plainly ſetting out the Truth, and indeavouring in the proper and regular way of a National Synod to have it reſtored at home. And therefore while he thought to do the Work and ſave his Life in the <hi>Cranmerian</hi> way of a Crafty Trick, he was ſuffered to loſe both his Deſign and it too. It is not a light matter <hi>to corrupt the Solemn Worſhip of God;</hi> or for thoſe in place of Authority knowingly to <hi>connive at ſuch Corruptions.</hi> Nor are matters of true <hi>Religion</hi> to be <hi>promoted by Tricks and underhand Dealings.</hi> I know none of the known <hi>Actors in the</hi> Cranmerian <hi>Corruptions,</hi> who liv'd long after, or came not to unhappy ends. And <hi>the preſent Governors of this Church</hi> have had ſufficient warning to have reſtored the Honour of God, and prevented the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of ſo much of their own Shame. <hi>Sins of Omiſſion</hi> in places of great Truſt are dangerous and damnable: And ſuch is frequently the State of ſuch as joyn with them. And this undoubtedly has been a <hi>continual Gratification</hi> to the Powers of darkneſs to have held this Nation in ſuch Fetters ſo long.</p>
            <p>But becauſe <hi>the Gratifications</hi> of thoſe Apoſtate Spirits ariſe from their Succeſs in their attempts upon Men, to involve them in Sin and Diſobedience and Indignities to God, and ſo engage them in their own ſtate of Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, they cannot be well underſtood, unleſs <hi>the Wickedneſs of what was done</hi> in this matter be farther detected and explained, than is commonly appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. For which purpoſe it is to be noted, that it was uſual with <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind</hi> from the beginning to perform their moſt <hi>Solemn Tranſactions</hi> with all the external <hi>Declarations</hi> of their Minds that they could; that is, not only with <hi>Audible,</hi> but alſo with <hi>Viſible</hi> Signs and Significations; not with Words
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37717:4"/>only, but with the conjuction of Actions and Things; and the Omiſſion of thoſe was interpreted to be a Slight or Contempt. Accordingly it was uſual to make their <hi>Addreſſes</hi> to God, and even to Princes and Prophets, with <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents</hi> in Recognition of Superiority. And the chief Aliments of their Lives, <hi>Bread and Wine,</hi> were uſually part of their Offerings, even at their Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. This was retained by <hi>the Jews,</hi> who at all their Feſtivals conſecrated a Cake of Bread, and a Chalice of Wine with Water, and over it gave Thanks to God, for his Creation of the World, and his ſpecial Mercies to Mankind, and to themſelves, particularly mention'd, and more largly for that Celebrated at that time. This is what God foretold by the Prophet, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. ſhould be done by <hi>the Gentiles;</hi> and this is the import of our Saviours words, <hi>as often as ye do this, do it in Commemoration of me,</hi> whereby he appropriates this, which was uſed before in Commemoration of ſeveral other Divine Favours, to be done always from thence forward in Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of his Sacrifice upon the Croſs, as the Compendium of all. And from this Inſtitution the Apoſtles, and from them the Churches founded by them receiv'd it, and have ever ſince uſed it, as <hi>an Antitype,</hi> as effectual for them to all intents and purpoſes, as were all the Types and Sacrifices of the Jews for them before his Paſſion.</p>
            <p>But more particularly therein may be obſerved, 1. A ſolemn <hi>Recognition</hi> of the Soveraignty of God by right of Creation, in the <hi>Oblation</hi> of the chief A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments of our Lives, with Thankſgivings for it, and all his Divine Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. 2. The <hi>Sanctification</hi> of thoſe Creatures by the Deſcent of the Holy Spirit at the Prayers of the Church. 3. The <hi>Oblation of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures Sanctified</hi> in Commemoration of the Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſs, the great Propitiation for the Sins of the World, by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone we have Acceſs unto, and Acceptance with the Father, with Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, Prayers, and Interceſſions for all Men, according to the Apoſtles Exhortation, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. So that the Oblation of the Memorials of his Son's Paſſion, is a <hi>Solemn Actual Allegation</hi> of his Covenant, (<hi>v. Gen.</hi> 9.13.17. And therein is implyed. 4. A Solemn <hi>Recognition</hi> of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by him, <hi>Subjection</hi> to him, and <hi>Obligation</hi> to lay down our Lives in Obedience to him, as he did his for us in obedience to his Father; and a Solemn Act of <hi>Confederation</hi> with him. And laſtly, the <hi>Communion</hi> and Participation of theſe Sanctified Creatures for the Sanctification of our Souls and Bodies, and Augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spiritual Life and Vigor, and Special Application of all the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of his Holy Sacrifice unto us.</p>
            <p>And now, what could be either more honorable for our Saviour, or a more Solemn Engagement with him on the one ſide, or more offenſive and grievous to that Envious and Malicious Spirit on the other, than to ſee that Paſſion, which he had moſt maliciouſly procur'd to be ſo honour'd, and applied to the Honour of the Holy Trinity, and the Benefit and Advantage of Men, and turned to his own Confuſion, and his quondam Vaſſals and their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity thus confederating and fortified againſt him? And what could be a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:37717:4"/>greater <hi>Gratification</hi> to him, then to ſee all this, which was ſo offenſive and grievous, and done weekly at leaſt in all Churches, and dayly in all great Churches, to be thus Aboliſhed, and even what remained of it, ſoon after almoſt every where neglected?</p>
            <p>And this is what their Grandfather <hi>Cranmer,</hi> or rather this wicked Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by him, and in him, was ſo ſubtle and induſtrious to aboliſh: And this is what the preſent <hi>Cranmerians,</hi> his Poſterity, have ſo obſtinately oppoſed, and refuſe to reſtore, notwithſtanding the Publick Admonition, raiſed and conducted by the hand of God undoubtedly, into the very heart of the Chief City of the Nation, notwithſtanding the Fortifications of Humane Laws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it; and although divers learned men have declared their Convictions of the truth of the Caſe in print; but to no other effect, than their own ſelf Condemnation, and Condemnation of the reſt, and plain Manifeſtation of what Spirit they are. And here we may plainly perceive the Reaſon of what <hi>Mr. Mede</hi> hath well obſerv'd in fact, That the Devil hath exerciſed and vented more Malice and Spight againſt this Holy Rite, than againſt any other part of the Chriſtian Religion, except the Doctrine of the Holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. And from hence alone it is abundantly manifeſt, that it was the ſame Spirit, or of the ſame party, which ſecretly inſpir'd and inſtigated <hi>Cranmar,</hi> and which more openly diſputed with <hi>Luther</hi> before, againſt it. And this I think is ſufficient for Satisfaction to the Firſt Queſtion.</p>
            <p>But we have not yet ſeen all the inveterate Spight and Malice of this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Spirit againſt this Holy Solemnity: That could not ſatisfie it thus to have depraved and aboliſhed it, and deprived God, the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit of the Honor, and the Chriſtian People of the Benefit, of it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he could prevail alſo to have a piece of <hi>Mockery</hi> ſet up in the place of it: Such another as was heretofore introduced in <hi>France,</hi> called <hi>Miſſa Sicca,</hi> but ſoon exploded there, as a dry, empty, barren thing; but ſet up here, upon ſome occaſion taken from the firſt Book of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. very formally in the latter, inlarged with the Prieſts Reherſal of the <hi>Ten Commandments,</hi> and a ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Reſpons for the People, at the end of each; and commonly call'd the <hi>Second Service.</hi> The <hi>Subtilty</hi> of the Serpent is remarkable enough in it, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing but what is innocent and good and well accomodated to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people, and make them believe it as good as what they had before; but being perform'd at the Altar, and in the place of that Auguſt, Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as S. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> calls it Tremendous Sacrifice, it was an Abominable <hi>Abuſe</hi> both to God and Man. As if a Tenant ſhould with great formality preſent to his Lord at a great Feaſt at his own Table, for a Basket of choice Fruit, an Empty Basket. And yet is this Abuſe of a ſhadow continued very formally in moſt Churches in <hi>England,</hi> and the Subſtance neglected: A very pleaſant Spectacle undoubtedly to Troops of <hi>Apoſtate Spirits,</hi> and a ſpecial Invitation and <hi>Gratification</hi> to them to come and attend ſuch a Service in the place of the <hi>Good Angels,</hi> who offended at ſuch an Abuſe are moſt likely to withdraw their Preſence. The Indignity done to God, and to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:37717:5"/>in this, is greater than I think fit to inlarge upon: but there is one thing I think fit the People ſhould be admoniſhed of: The Chriſtian Church, as I take it, hath always looked upon this Holy Solemnity, as a Repreſentation upon Earth, in the beſt manner Mortals can perform it, of what our Great High Prieſt doth for us in Heaven, in a Divine and Spiritual manner. And how can they expect the Compleat, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed any Benefit of what he doth there, who ſet up ſuch a lame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Abuſe of it here? I do much ſuſpect that both the <hi>Greek and Latine Churches</hi> for 1200 years laſt paſt have ſuffer'd much for their <hi>Curtelling a Conſiderable part of this Office;</hi> as may eaſily be perceived by comparing all their Liturgies now in uſe, with that moſt ancient Form in the Conſtitutions, and the moſt ancient Uſages of the Jews: And what theſe incorrigible Cranmerians have farther to expect, they may do well to conſider.</p>
            <p>There remains ſtill <hi>a Conſiderable part of the Subtilty</hi> of the Serpent for Securing, by the Power of the Beaſt, the Advantages he hath gotten by the Treachery of the Falſe Prophet and Unfaithfulneſs of the Whore: but what hath been obſerved already being abundantly ſufficient for a ground of <hi>Anſwer to the remaining Queſtions,</hi> the Conſideration of this may be more ſeaſonable upon another occaſion: as the <hi>Cranmerian Hereſy.</hi> or <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since therefore both the Subtilty and the Malice of the Adverſary, the Devil, is ſo manifeſt in the Alterations aforeſaid, againſt this Holy Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and there in againſt the Holy Trinity, the Sacrifice of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our upon the Croſs, the Communion of Saints, the Holy Catholic Church; and the Church of <hi>England</hi> in particular, <hi>the Anſwers</hi> to all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Queſtions are very eaſy, plain, full, and yet Short: That all, who have any regard to their Baptiſmal Covenant and the Renunciation therein of the Devil and all his works, to the moſt tremendous Denounciations of our Saviour, the Admonitions of his Apoſtles after his Aſcenſion, or the Salvation of their own Souls, muſt abſtain from all Communion or Participation in theſe Corruptions and Abuſes, after Notice of them, be they of the Clergy or Laity: And if they be <hi>Prieſts,</hi> muſt celebrate this Holy Sacrifice, as often as they can have a competent number of qualified Communicants in the compleateſt Form, they can procure; ſuch as The firſt book of <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. The Scotch Liturgy, The Liturgy of the Ancients repreſented in Engliſh Forms, or ſome Tranſlation out of the Ancient Forms, or Compoſure according to them, Notwithſtanding any temporal Laws, Cannons or Subſcription to the contrary: And if of the Laity, have recourſe to ſuch as do ſo; and abſtain in the mean time, and employ ſo much the more time in Prayer to God, who is not tyed to his own Ordinances, to ſupply by his Grace their want of Opportunity, and to reſtore his H. Worſhip to its due Integrity and Frequency in Publick; and to provide for them at leaſt in private in the mean time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37717:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
